<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The falshood of the cheife grounds of the Romish religion Descried and convinced in a briefe answere to certaine motiues sent by a priest to a gentleman to induce him to turne papist. By W.S.</title>
            <title>Seminary priest put to a non-plus</title>
            <author>Sutton, William, 1561 or 2-1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100149</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836001</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836001</idno>
            <idno type="VID">240</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13210)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1293:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The falshood of the cheife grounds of the Romish religion Descried and convinced in a briefe answere to certaine motiues sent by a priest to a gentleman to induce him to turne papist. By W.S.</title>
                  <title>Seminary priest put to a non-plus</title>
                  <author>Sutton, William, 1561 or 2-1632.</author>
                  <author>Sutton, William, b. 1607 or 8.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 122 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>L. Lichfield],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed for the author Anno Dom. 1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A corrected edition of: Sutton, William, senior.  A seminary priest put to a non-plus.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Edited by the author's son; since William Sutton, senior, died in 1632, the "author" referred to in the imprint is probably his son.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:240:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:240:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> FALSHOOD OF THE CHEIFE grounds of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Religion.</p>
            <p>Deſcried and convinced in a briefe Anſwere to certaine Motiues ſent by a Prieſt to a Gentleman <hi>to induce him to turne Papiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By W.S.</p>
            <p>Printed for the Author <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1635.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:240:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:240:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL his much honoured Vncle EDWARD SMYTH <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are other reaſons beſides that common motiue, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular pretence of the importunity of friends, which hath now put this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle manuall into the world. It was compoſed by the Author (for I cannot ſay
<pb facs="tcp:240:3"/>that it was written by him, but rather dictated as hee ſpake it) lying on his bed of ſickneſſe: and therefore hee intended to haue kept it pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, iudging it vnworthy other mens approbation, becauſe vnworthy his own. Nevertheleſſe it ſecretly crept into the preſſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd from thence full of faults like the Printer of it, who had as little authority to Print it at all, as Print it falſe. There was no other way to ſuppreſſe the old impreſſion, but by a new, which I haue here done, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it out the ſecond time, but in a leſſe volumne, and with leſſe faults.</p>
            <p>There is one motiue more,
<pb facs="tcp:240:3"/>and that more important then the former. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſince his death (for in his life time malice it ſelfe was never ſo audacious as to dare ecclipſe the bight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his integrity either in life or doctrine) hath had his faith branded with the name of apoſtacy, and his profeſſion with hereſy. But whither he were a profeſſed open enemy, or an hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall friend, which hath done him this wrong, I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to name. Whoſoever he were, this enſuing treatiſe will put him both to ſhame and ſilence; and therefore I need not make any apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy for him, whoſe owne
<pb facs="tcp:240:4"/>workes ſpeake in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p>Sir! it was formerly made ſolely yours by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and therefore in the dedication it now iuſtly claimes your patronage on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. If it ſatisfy not the more curious reader, yet hee that made it, thought his paines fully recompenced in that it gaue you ſatisfaction; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the reward of my labour ſpread it ſelfe vnto others, but is wholy termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated in your acceptance. If it chance to bee condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as imperfect, becauſe he hath not ſpoken all, that might haue beene ſaid on this ſubiect; I adde, neither
<pb facs="tcp:240:4"/>hath he ſpoken all that hee could. It was intended for a letter only, and therefore not to ſwell into a larger volumne; yet I preſume there is as much in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, as the Prieſts motiues require, &amp; more peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then he ever expected, or at leaſt thank't him for. Such as it is, it is once more made yours by him, who deſires to be eſteemed</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your dutifull Nephew and Servant <hi>WILLIAM SVTTON.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From Chriſt-Church in Oxon.
<date>
                     <hi>Iun.</hi> 28. 1635.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:240:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:240:5"/>
            <head>Motiues ſent by a Prieſt to a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, to Induce him <hi>to turne Papiſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The rejection of the Iewes and acceptation of the Gentiles.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Haue no will in you,<note place="margin">How to knovv the holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique. Church which all Chriſtians profeſſe to beleeue.</note> ſaith the Lord of <hi>Hoſtes,</hi> and guift I will not receiue of your hands, for from the riſing of the Sunne to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe, great is my name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and in every place there is Sacrificing, and there is offered to my name a cleane oblation, becauſe my name is great amongſt the Gentiles,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:240:6"/>ſaith the Lord of Hoſtes. <hi>Mal. 1. verſ. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Deſcription of the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Catholique Church Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The holy Chriſtian Catholique Church militant, which wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in the Apoſtles Creed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, is a viſible Monarchy or Kingdome conſiſting of all the true beleeuers vpon the face of the earth, confeſſing one God in Trinity, and Trinity in Vnity, vnder one lawfull viſible head for the time being, obſeruing one Faith, Religion, and Sacraments, inſtituted by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Which holy kingdome and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, is compoſed of a viſible head, Clergy and Laity, the head to governe, the Clergy to preach and adminiſter Sacraments, the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:240:6"/>Laity to learne and to obey in all things touching their faith and ſalvation: For Chriſt ſaith of the Paſtors of his Church, <hi>Hee that heareth you, heareth mee, and he that deſpiſeth you, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth mee,</hi> Luk. <hi>10.</hi> verſ. <hi>16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That our Saviour Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Prieſt for ever <hi>ſecundum ordinem Melchiſedec,</hi> was the firſt viſible head, and founder of the ſaid holy Chriſtian Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church militant compoſed of a head, Clergy, and Laity is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, firſt in his ſacred perſon, being the viſible head, in his holy Apoſtles being the Clergy, and in his Common diſciples being the Laity, which ſmall beginning is compared to a Muſtard-ſeed, and the increaſing to a great tree, that birds may build in the Branches thereof, our Saviour ſaying to the Clergy his Apoſtles; and in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:240:7"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all their lawfull Succeſſors, <hi>To you it is giuen to know the miſteries of the Kingdome of God, but to the reſt in Parables.</hi> Luk. <hi>8.</hi> verſ. <hi>10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The increaſing of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Preaching and Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our Saviour Chriſt and his Apoſtles, many were conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be members of the Church. At S. <hi>Peters</hi> firſt Sermon after he had receiued the Holy Ghoſt <hi>3000.</hi> were added, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>5000. Act. 2. verſ. 41. Act. 4. verſ. 4.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> affirmeth, that in his time the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane faith was renowned in the whole world. <hi>Rom. 1. verſ. 8.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with the words of Chriſts <hi>But you ſhall receiue the vertue of the holy Ghoſt comming vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, and you ſhall bee Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:240:7"/>to me in Ieruſalem, and in all Iurie and Samaria, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the vtmoſt of the earth.</hi> Act, <hi>1.</hi> v. <hi>8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the Continuance of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catholique Church in true Faith, by the Holy Ghoſts aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is my Covenant with thee ſaith our Lord, speaking of his Church, my ſpirit that is in thee, and my words that I haue put in thy mouth ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, and out of the mouth of thy ſeed, and out of the mouth of thy ſeedes ſeed, ſaith our Lord, from this preſent and for ever, <hi>Iſay 59. verſ. 21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All power is giuen to mee in Heaven and in Earth, going therefore teach ye all Nations baptizing them in the name of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:240:8"/>Father, and of the Sonne, and of the Holy Ghoſt, teaching them to obſerue all things whatſoever I haue commanded you, and behold J am with you alwaies to the Conſummation of the World, <hi>Math. 28. verſ. 19.20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will aske the Father and hee will giue you another Paraclet, that he may abide with you for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the spirit of truth. <hi>Ioh. 14. verſ. 16.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if hee will not heare the Church, let him be to thee as the Heathen, and as the Publican, <hi>Math. 18. v. 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All which promiſes of Chriſt, for ſending the Holy Ghoſt to preſerue his Church in truth for ever, was viſibly &amp; miraculouſly performed on Whitſunday,</hi> Act. <hi>2.</hi> verſ. <hi>1.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:240:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That our Saviour Chriſt did conſtitute Saint</hi> Peter <hi>to bee Miniſteriall head of his Church militant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I ſay to thee, thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> and vpon this rocke will I build my Church, and the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it, and J will giue to thee the Keyes of the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and whatſoever thou ſhalt bind vpon earth it ſhall bee bound alſo in the heavens, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thou ſhalt looſe in earth, it ſhall be looſed alſo in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, <hi>Math. 16. v. 18.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And our Saviour ſaid; <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Simon,</hi> behold Satan hath required to haue thee for to ſift as wheat, But I haue prayed for thee, that thy faith faile not, and thou being converted confirme thy Brothren. <hi>Luk. 22. v. 31.32.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:240:9"/>
            <p>Our Saviour Chriſt asking <hi>Peter,</hi> if he loued him more then theſe, ſaid, yea Lord, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt I loue thee, whereupon Chriſt ſaid to him twice, feed my Lambes and the third time feede my Sheepe. <hi>Ioh. 21. v. 15.16.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Saint</hi> Peter <hi>was chiefe of the Apoſtles and the firſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When all the holy Apoſtles are named, S. <hi>Peter</hi> is the firſt, <hi>Math. 10. verſ. 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Apoſtles had viſibly receiued the Holy Ghoſt, S. <hi>Peter</hi> made the firſt Sermon thereof, whereat <hi>3000.</hi> perſons were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, <hi>Act. 2. v. 41.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With his word and power, he killed <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> for their Sacriledge, <hi>Act. 5. v. 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:240:9"/>
            <p>Saiut <hi>Peter</hi> called the firſt Councell of the Apoſtles held at Ieruſalem, and firſt ſpake there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, <hi>Act. 15. v. 7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jt is affirmed by old writers and ſome moderne learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants; that S. <hi>Peter</hi> was <hi>15.</hi> yeares Biſhop of Rome, and by the auncient Eccleſiaſticall wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> were both of them martyred to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in Rome vnder the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Nero. Orig. apud Euſeb. Lib. 3. cap. 1. Euſ. Cap. 24. Lib. 2. Hiſt. Eccliaſtic. Tertul. de praeſc. c. 26. Aug. tract. 123 in Ioh. Chryſoſt. &amp; Beda in hunc locum. S. Ambr. Serm. 66.68. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Maximus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Statu faelix Eccleſia, cui to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam doctrinam Apoſtoli cum ſuo fanguine pro funderunt, vbi Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus paſſioni Dominicae adaequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:240:10"/>vbi Paulus Iohannis exitu Coronatur. Tertul. de Praeſcrip. cap. 36.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> Peters <hi>Succeſſors Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome haue exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed chiefe authority in the Church Militant ever ſince to this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Martyrdome of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> Peter, firſt Biſhop of Rome, <hi>32.</hi> of the ſucceeding Biſhops there were martyred for the faith of Chriſt. <hi>Euſebius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Victor</hi> in the firſt <hi>200.</hi> yeares excommunicated the <hi>Aſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Biſhops about the obſervation or keeping Eaſter day.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Silveſter 314.</hi> yeeres cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the firſt Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Arian hereſte.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:240:10"/>
            <p>Pope <hi>Damaſus 367.</hi> called the ſecond generall Councell at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> againſt <hi>Macedonius</hi> the heretique.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Caeleſtine 414.</hi> called the third generall Councell at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> againſt <hi>Neſtorius</hi> the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Leo 440.</hi> called the fourth generall Councell at <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> againſt the heretique <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And likewiſe euer ſince to the laſt generall Councell of Trent, the Biſhops of Rome haue called them all, as hereſies and falſe Prophets did ariſe in the Church.</p>
            <p>Jt is confeſſed by divers lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Protestants that the Roman Church was the true Mother Church, which Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:240:11"/>planted ſome for <hi>300.</hi> yeares, ſome for <hi>400.</hi> yeares, ſome for <hi>600.</hi> yeares and ſome for <hi>800</hi> yeares after Chriſt, which being true, that it was once the true Church, and alſo true, that our Saviour Chriſt promiſed to bee with it to the conſummation of the world, and to ſend the ſpirit of Truth to abide with it for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and that Hell gates ſhould not preuaile againſt it; and Chriſt ſaith, Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe, but my words ſhall not paſſe; How then can it be true that the Roman Church being once the true mother Church ſhould fall ſo fouly from her firſt puritie, as is by ſome too too boldly affirmed?</p>
            <p>Jt is ſo neceſſary for every one to know and beliene the holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church Militant, that whoſoever is not a ſound member of that ſociety either in act or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:240:11"/>cannot be ſaved, as all thoſe which were out of <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke were drowned.</p>
            <p>And to end with a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all the Patriarchall &amp; Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall Seas of the Apoſtles be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed and worne out many hundred yeares ſince by Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques and Jnfidels, onely the Church of Rome the Seate of <hi>Saint Peter</hi> ſtands at this day moſt conſpicuous, according to the prayer and promiſe of Chriſt; that his faith ſhould not faile, and that the gates of Hell ſhould not prevaile againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus briefly is proued, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, encreaſing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing of the holy Chriſtian Catholique Apoſtolique and Romane Church; as alſo the promiſed continuall aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of truth to remaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:240:12"/>alwaies to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of the World, that is for ever. Of which Vine all Chriſtians that ſhall be ſaued muſt be vnited liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly branches and members,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:240:12"/>
            <head>THE ANSWERE to the Prieſts <hi>Motiues.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Brother?</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he was that ſent you theſe lines as motiues to make you a Romiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, I muſt needs thinke him your <hi>friend,</hi> (and by that name I meane to call him here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after) becauſe I thinke hee did it out of a deſire to ſaue your ſoule: although I am ſure he goes the wrong way to worke:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:240:13"/>And if you ſhould follow him (which God forbid) hee will certainly leade you into the ditch. Though his proofes bee ſimple ones, (as I hope you will ſee by the anſwere) yet it ſeemes, hee thought better of them, and they were the beſt he knew; and therefore if hee faile in his purpoſe (as I hope he ſhall) yet you haue ſome cauſe to thanke him, in that hee vſed the ſame arguments to perſwade you, wherewith hee himſelfe was perſwaded. But for the validity of his reaſons doe you judge your ſelfe, when you haue heard vs both ſpeake, or if not, <hi>let it bee tried by God and the country.</hi> And who ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he was he hath placed a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the foot of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which for the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancie thereof deſerved to bee ſet in a higher roome: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:240:13"/>I will begin with that firſt.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The true Catholique Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>(Jt is ſo neceſſary</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>for every one to know and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the holy Catholique Church militant, that whoſoever is not a ſound member of that ſociety ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in act or deſire, cannot bee ſaved.)</hi> All this is true, and there is great reaſon for it; for if it were once agreed among Chriſtians which were the true Church of Chriſt, other diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in Religion would more eaſily be compoſed by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority thereof. But ſo long as the doubt remaines concerning the Church it ſelfe (as in theſe daies that is the capitall contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie betweene Proteſtants &amp; Papiſts) there is ſmall hope of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good accord vnleſſe both ſides could agree vpon ſome
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:240:14"/>third party to be vmpire: Who muſt be ſuch a one as is of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vnderſtanding to diſcerne where the truth reſteth, and withall of that indifferency in affection, that he encline no way to one ſide more then to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; For that either the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh or reformed Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues the parties liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, that they ſhould require to be made Iudges in their own cauſe (though ſome of our adver ſaries be not aſhamed to make ſuch a propoſition) yet I thinke there is no man that hath his fiue wits about him, but will deteſt the impudency thereof at the firſt hearing. Of neceſſity therefore ſome third party muſt be thought vpon, who being no way intreſſed in either faction, is of ſufficient Iudgement to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine which of the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders make the beſt claime; now
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:240:14"/>though wee ſhould ſearch the whole world over with a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, there is none ſuch poſſibly to be found vnder heaven, but only the holy Scripture: which being confeſſed by both ſides to be the rule of faith, cannot well be denied to be the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Iudge for deciding of all doubts in that kinde ariſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the faithfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Scripture a competent judge of the true Church.</head>
               <p>And for this queſtion of the Church S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> is peremptory, that there is no other way to determine it but by Scripture alone; </p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jnter nos &amp; Donatiſtas quaeſtio eſt vbi ſit Eccleſia</hi> (iuſt as it is now <hi>inter nos &amp; Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas) quîd ergo facturi ſumus? in verbis noſtris eam quaeſituri, an in verbis capitis ſui? Puto quòd in illius potius verbis cam
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:240:15"/>quaerere debemus: lib. de vnit. </hi>
                  </p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eccleſ. c.</hi> 2.</bibl>
               </q>
               <p> That whole chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter together with the 3. and 4. following is altogether to the ſame purpoſe; nay <hi>Bellar.</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe denies not but in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the Scripture is better knowne to vs then the Church, and <hi>ex hac hypotheſi,</hi> when the Church is doubted of he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to grant, that wee muſt ſeeke for it in the Scripture, <hi>de Eccleſ. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 2. And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this faire weather that he makes with Scripture, there is neither hee, nor any of the reſt that are willing to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it for Iudge in this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie; the moſt they will yeeld, is to accept it for a rule of faith, and yet they ſtand not to that neither, when they require <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> to be joyned vnto it, as if without the helpe thereof it could not meaſure perfectly.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:240:15"/>For <hi>Regula &amp; regulatum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent eſſe adaequata.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ſcripture.</note> If Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alone bee not ſufficient of it ſelfe to meaſure the length of à Chriſtians faith, vnleſſe tradition bee added to helpe, then it is no rule at all, much leſſe a perfect rule, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a peece of one. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they are content ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time for faſhion ſake to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Scripture for the rule of faith in part, yet by no meanes will they allow it for a Iudge, though that be the very name, whereby <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> and the Fathers of thoſe times, did vſually call it,
<q> 
                     <hi>Iſta contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſia Iudicem requirit</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de nup. &amp; concup. c.</hi> 33. <hi>Iudicet ergo Chriſtus Iudicet cum illo &amp; Apoſtolus: quia in Apoſtolo ipſe loquîtur Chriſtus:</hi> and againe, <hi>de gratiâ &amp; lib. arbit. c.</hi> 18. <hi>Sedeat inter
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:240:16"/>nos iudex Apostolus Iohannes.</hi> and <hi>Optatus contra Parmen. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Quaerendi ſunt iudices,</hi> ſaith he: <hi>Jn terris de hâc re nullum poterit reperiri iudicium.</hi>
                  </q> (You ſee by this, that the Pope was not acknowledged in thoſe daies for the judge of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, &amp; if <hi>Optatus</hi> had beene a Papiſt, he durſt not haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſuch a word) but marke how hee goes on:
<q>
                     <hi>De coelo quaerendus eſt judex: ſed quid pulſamus ad coelum, cùm habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus hic in Evangelio Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum?</hi>
                  </q> the place is too long to bee all ſet downe, and that which followeth, is all to that purpoſe. Our adverſaries ſpeake in another language now adaies, then <hi>Optatus</hi> or <hi>Auguſtine</hi> or any of thoſe holy Fathers were wont to ſpeake. When they ſaid ſo often, <hi>Judicet Chriſtus &amp; Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicet Scriptura,</hi> they would haue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:240:16"/>ſaid once at the leaſt, <hi>Iudicet Papa,</hi> if they had imagined that any ſuch power had belonged vnto him. Here was a fit oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for them to haue decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelues true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques. But alas, good men, how could they ſpeake of that which they knew not, or how could they teach that doctrine to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that they were never taught themſelues? For this vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart judge, it is a meere novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a later edition vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to the Chriſtian world in thoſe daies, like that gibbriſh tongue, which ſome mungrell Iews ſpake, &amp; Neh emias com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of <hi>c.</hi> 13.24. <hi>In ſcripturis didicimus Chriſtum: in ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris didicimus Eccleſiam. Aug. ep.</hi> 166. <hi>&amp; de vnitat. Eccleſ. c.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>Now when we ſay, that the Scripture is judge, wee doe not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:240:17"/>refuſe to heare the voice of the Church, ſpeaking in the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Miniſtery of her lawfull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, &amp; interpreting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures vnto vs. Wee know that there are many texts full of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, and aboue the reach of common vnderſtanding: nay, there are many which his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe himſelfe, I am ſure, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands not for all his infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble chaire. But we know with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that there are other places of Scripture, ſo facil and plaine, as a man of ordinary capacity may ſafely be his owne inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter: and there is nothing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation, either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning faith or life, but that in ſome one place or other, it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered in ſuch plaine manner, as every man may vnderſtand it: if Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> deceiue vs not <hi>de Doctr. Chriſt. l.</hi> 2, <hi>c.</hi> 9. And many other of the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:240:17"/>as well as hee. And therefore if blinde men ſee not the ſunne, it is not the fault of the ſun, but theirs, whoſe eyes the God of this world hath blinded.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>A lawfull Councell the Church repreſentatiue.</head>
               <p>Now for thoſe places of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which are of greateſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, if we ſeeke for a vocall judge to interpret them vnto vs, it is certaine that there is none ſufficient to informe vpon earth the conſcience of a Chriſtian, but only a lawfull Councell, which is fitly therefore called the <hi>Church repreſentatiue.</hi> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſeveral Paſtors though never ſo learned &amp; godly, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a probability: but the vniforme conſent of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all joyned together in a lawfull Councell, doth conclude a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:240:18"/>of truth in that that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. What conditions belong to a lawfull Councell I will not now ſtand to inquire. Some ſuch there haue beene heretofore (though not ſo many as, would be thought ſo) and ſome there may be againe.</p>
               <p>In the meane time,<note place="margin">A councell the higheſt iudgement vpon earth.</note> I deſire you to thinke that Proteſtants aſcribe farre greater authority by many degrees to the voice of the Church ſpeaking in ſuch aſſemblies, then Papiſts doe for all their great talking; and yet you muſt know, that there are divers learned Papiſts of the ſame opinion with Proteſtants in this point; namely, that the iudgement of a <hi>lawfull Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell is to bee reputed the higheſt iudgement vpon earth, whether the Pope giue his conſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto or no.</hi> The Ieſuites labour hard on the contrary ſide to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:240:18"/>draw all to the Papall chayre, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the ſentence of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell to be of no validity, vnleſſe the Pope doe approoue it, which in effect is nothing elſe, but to abuſe the name of Councels, and of the Church, making them meere ſtales to ſerue the Popes turne;<note place="margin">Differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces amongſt the Papiſts.</note> ſee the differences that are among themſelues about this matter in <hi>Bel, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de conc. c.</hi> 14.17. and the baſe conceit the Ieſuites hold of all ſuch Councells as want the Popes confirmation: contrary to the judgement of <hi>Peter de Alliaco,</hi> Cardinall of <hi>Cambry, Iohn Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Iacobus Almaine,</hi> Card. <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanus,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Toſtatus,</hi> Abbot <hi>Panormitan,</hi> with the Councels of <hi>Piſa, Conſtance,</hi> and <hi>Baſil,</hi> and generally of the whole French Church <hi>at this day.</hi> I know not to which of theſe factions your <hi>friend</hi> enclines: if he thinke as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:240:19"/>the French Papiſts doe, I am of his opinion; if hee be Ieſuited, deſire him to mend his deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Catholique Church; and where he names it (a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Monarch</hi>) let him ſit downe and write <hi>(a viſible Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch.)</hi> For that is <hi>Purus putus Ieſuitiſmus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diſput. Theol. To. <hi>3.</hi> diſ. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> By the Church we meane her head (ſaith <hi>Greg. de Valent.</hi>) that is the Pope: in whom there reſideth the full authority of the Church, when he pleaſeth to determine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith, whether he doe it with a Councell or without. His words are theſe: <hi>Eſt in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiâ authoritas divinitûs inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuta, quâ fideles tum doctrinâ, tum praeceptis informentur: Haec authoritas, plenè in Romano Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice Chriſti <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icario, &amp;</hi> S. <hi>Petri ſucceſſore reſidet, qui ſcilicet de fidei &amp; morum controverſiis vel per ſe, vel vnà cum generali con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:240:19"/>ſufficienter conſtituat. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Eccleſiae intelligimus eius caput, id eſt, Romanum Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficem per ſe—</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I haue ſtood thus long vpon the authority of Scripture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if the queſtion of the Church muſt receiue its deciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from thence, as <hi>Bell</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, me thinkes it is but hard dealing in him and his fellowes to keepe Lay-people from the free reading of the scripture; vnleſſe they meane to keepe them from the knowledge of the true Church alſo; but for your <hi>friend</hi> though hee talke much of the Catholique Church, yet I cannot finde by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, that ever hee conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted either with ſcripture or any ancient lawfull councell, when he went about it. And thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I would preſently ioyne iſſue with him, but that I am bound
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:240:20"/>to take knowledge firſt of a place of <hi>Malachy,</hi> which hee ſets moſt eminently in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front of his writing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I haue no will in you ſaith the Lord of Hoſtes, and gift I will not receiue of your hand; for from the riſing of the Sunne to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe great is my name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Gentiles, and in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place there is ſacrificing, and there is offered to my name a cleane oblation, becauſe my name is great amongſt the Gentiles, ſaith the Lord of Hoſtes. Mal.</hi> 1.11.</p>
               <p>In the allegation of this Text I complaine, that there are two notorious faults committed by him. 1. That he alledgeth it to no purpoſe: any other text in the Bible would haue become the place as well as that. 2. That he falſifies the words of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:240:20"/>Prophet, and makes him to ſay that which he never meant.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If your <hi>friend</hi> in citing theſe words, did purpoſe to proue the reiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Iews, and calling of the Gentiles, I know it is true; but I know not to what purpoſe alledged, to perſwade any man to Popery more then the depoſing of <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athar,</hi> and <hi>Sadocks</hi> advancement to the Prieſthood, 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.35. If his meaning be to ſhew that the Church of the Gentiles is of greater extent then ever the Iewiſh Synagogue was, &amp; that it is not now confined to any one place, or people, as it was vnder the Law, but belongeth indifferently to all Nations vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, for my part, I know no Chriſtian that ever denied it beſides the Donatiſts of old, and ſome Papiſts of later times, who ſeeking to bring all Chriſtians
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:240:21"/>to a dependance vpon Rome, and the Biſhop of that place (juſt as the Synagogue depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the Temple of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem and the high Prieſt there) they turne the vniverſal Church into a particular congregation, howſoever for faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſake they retaine the name of Catholike. They themſelues doe in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner acknowledge as much, when as not contenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with thoſe known marks of <hi>Vna, Sancta, Catholica, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolica,</hi> by which the Church was wont to bee notified in the antient Creeds, and Councels, they foiſt in <hi>Romana</hi> amongſt the reſt, which being but a late tricke vnheard of in antiquity, and only deviſed to ſerue the preſent turne, it ſhewes that the Church for whoſe ſake it was firſt deviſed, is but of a late edition, <hi>per Romanam Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:240:21"/>nemo vnquam intellexit vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſalem niſi forte latini ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ignarus, Pigh. hierar Eccl. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. My ſecond accuſation is, that your <hi>friend</hi> deales not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in ſetting downe the words of <hi>Malachy.</hi> For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as hee makes the Prophet to ſay (<hi>that in every place there is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing)</hi> you may boldly tell him, that there is no one word of <hi>ſacrificing</hi> in the Hebrew text at all. God ſaith that among the Gentiles there ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe offered to his name; that is, prayers &amp; ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as you ſhall findethe word interpreted by the holy Ghoſt himſelfe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.8. and therefore the <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint,</hi> renders it by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; <hi>Arias Mont.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſſe.</note> (who vnderſtood both the Hebrew and Greeke very well) in his interlineary Bible tranſlates it <hi>incenſum.</hi> As
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:240:22"/>for <hi>Sacrificing,</hi> there is, <hi>Nec vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la nec veſtigium,</hi> neither fell, nor marke of it, as we ſay, in all that ſaying of the Prophet. You muſt thinke it was not without ſome ſpeciall cauſe, that the name of <hi>Sacrificing</hi> was drawne into the text, thus by the heeles, but vpon hope that it ſhould doe ſom ſpeciall ſervice: which though your <hi>friend</hi> doe not ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie (and ſo I need not take knowledge of it) yet I thinke good to make you acquainted withall, becauſe it may ſerue to diſcouer ſome other of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries myſteries. Cardinall <hi>Allen</hi> forſooth,<note place="margin">Card. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len.</hi>
                  </note> hath vndertaken out of theſe words of <hi>Malachy,</hi> to proue the ſacrifice of the Mas, by ſixe reaſons (which would make my writing ſwell too big if I ſhould ſet them all downe) <hi>lib. de Euch. c.</hi> 5. I would deſire you to reade both his reaſons, &amp;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:240:22"/>the anſwer made vnto them by Doct. <hi>Reinolds,</hi> in his confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with <hi>Hart.</hi> p. 479.<note place="margin">D. Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds and Hart.</note> And if you receiue not full ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in that point, beſides many others, blame me for commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the booke vnto you. Now what hope could hee ever haue of prouing the Sacrifice of the Maſſe by <hi>Malachy,</hi> vnleſſe the word <hi>Sacrifice</hi> it ſelfe were firſt found in the Text.</p>
               <p>And ſo I come to his deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Catholike Church as he calls it, though all things conſidered he hath little reaſon to giue it that name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>A deſcription of the Catholique Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The holy Chriſtian Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church militant, which we profeſſe in the Apoſtles Creed, to belieue, is a viſible Monarchy or Kingdome, conſiſting of all the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:240:23"/>true belieuers vpon the face of the earth, confeſſing one God in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and Trinity in Vnity, vnder one lawfull viſible head, for the time being, obſeruing one Faith, Religion and Sacraments inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt.</hi>— In which words let it bee no offence to ſay, that hee deales as boatmen vſe to doe, when they looke one way &amp; row another; for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he talkes of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, you ſhall finde preſently that hee meanes the Romiſh Church, a meere parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular one, though for the credit thereof he would faine yoake it together with the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique in the ſame deſcription. But ſee his ill lucke. For while he goes about to deſcribe them both in one, he failes to deſcribe either of them as he ſhould. For if the Catholique Church doth comprehend (as hee ſaith) the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:240:23"/>multitude of all true beleeuers even from righteous <hi>Abel</hi> (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh) to the end of the world, how can this agree to the Romiſh Church? On the other ſide, if it comprehend no more then ſuch as are ſubiect to one viſible head, how can the name of Catholique in right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto it? So this deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is like a ſhooe that will ſerue neither foote.</p>
               <p>If wee ſhould grant that the Romiſh faith in theſe daies were the true faith of Chriſt: yet could not that make their Church to bee the Catholique Church, but only a part thereof, and that is the moſt that can bee ſaid of it, though it were farre better then it is; but the Pope lookes higher then ſo, &amp; Rome ſcornes to be ranckt in the order of particular Churches. He muſt be the vniverſall Biſhop, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:240:24"/>ſhe the vniverſall Church of the World. For if that ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, what right hath either He, or Shee to claime ſubiection of thoſe, who haue their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dependance vpon other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops? Therefore to make this good, and to bring all fiſh into S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peters</hi> net, there were ſome well-wiſhers to the Romiſh cauſe, who not finding how two ſuch diſparates in nature, as vniverſall and particular, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique and ſingular, might poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be joyned together in one ſubiect, they found a meanes at laſt to joyne them both together in one word; and hence it comes to paſſe, that inſtead of <hi>Romana fides, &amp; Romana Eccleſia,</hi> which was wont to bee the common language among all Chriſtians, wee muſt call it henceforth, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano Catholicam fidem, Romana Catholicam Eccleſiam,</hi> or elſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:240:24"/>they will complaine that wee allow them not their full ſtile; Thus ſtill it falls out, that <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenta reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gignunt portenta ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum.</hi> And if it were not a new and ſtrange doctrine, it never needs to coine ſuch new and ſtrange words. And yet, as if <hi>Romana Eccleſia</hi> did not ſpeake home enough to expreſſe their meaning, or, as if it were too large a terme, and they durſt not truſt that more then <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica</hi> or <hi>Apoſtolica, Bellarmine de effect. ſacr. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 25. to be ſure to fit the ſhooe to the Popes foot, reſtraines it to <hi>nunc Romana Eccleſia:</hi> I know not what the ſpirit of giddineſſe is, if this bee not, or why wee ſhould not ſay of theſe men, as it was ſaid of the <hi>Arrians, Habent annuas &amp; menſtruas fides (Eccleſias.)</hi> If the ancient faith of Rome were the ſame with the preſent, what
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:240:25"/>meanes <hi>nunc Romana?</hi> if it were not, how is the preſent faith <hi>Catholica?</hi> For that onely is ſo, <hi>quae eſt omnium temporum &amp; lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum.</hi> The Councells of <hi>Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> or <hi>Trent</hi> will not be guided by the Councells of <hi>Baſil</hi> or <hi>Conſtance.</hi> And therefore <hi>Cuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ſpeakes plainely, and ſaies, that there is <hi>fides temporum,</hi> a faith that alters with the time, and that the true ſenſe of the Scripture is that, which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Church giues. <hi>Non eſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ſi praxis Eccleſiae vno tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore interpretetur ſcriptura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vno modo, &amp; alio tempore alio modo; nam intellectus currit cum praxi: intellectus enim, qui cum praxi concurrit, eſt ſpiritus vivificans: ſequuntur ergo Scripturae Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam &amp; non è converſo, Epiſt.</hi> 7. <hi>Bohem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The holy chriſtian Catholike Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">No abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</note> 
                  <hi>is a viſible Monarchie
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:240:25"/>vnder one viſible lawfull head,</hi> I complained before that the Church of Rome being a meere Particular, he made it all one to the Catholique Church of Chriſt. Here I finde cauſe to complaine on the other ſide, of his wrong done to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, when he termes it a viſible Monarchie, vnder a viſible Head: which is the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of a barre in her armes, and makes her no better then the Romiſh, or any other particular being of the younger houſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When hee names the Church a Monarchie, if he mean it in reſpect of Chriſt, ſole King and Monarch thereof, I will not contend with him about the name: or if hee meane it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of particular Churches we confeſſe, that in as much as they are ſubiect to their ſeverall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, their governement in that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:240:26"/>reſpect is a kinde of Monarchie, though not an abſolute Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, but ſuch a one as is tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with an Ariſtocraſie; becauſe Biſhops either doe not or ſhould not impoſe lawes vpon the Church, but <hi>Ex communi Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio Presbyterorum,</hi> by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and with the conſent of their Presbyterie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A viſible Monarchie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Not viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note>) If the Catholique Church were a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body, and not a myſticall: If it were ſome individuall and ſingular ſubiect, and not a meere vniverſall (as the name of a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique imports) Viſibility might well bee an adiunct be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing vnto it. Which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, I confeſſe, I vnderſtand not how it ſhould, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, they that ſpeake moſt of it vnderſtand it as little; if your <hi>friend</hi> haue ever ſeene the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church with his eye,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:240:26"/>let him ſay whether it be <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanum</hi> or <hi>adiaphanum, lumino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum corpus,</hi> or <hi>opacum;</hi> bid him tell you of what colour and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion it is. And doe not thinke I ieſt in mouing ſuch queſtions, for in good earneſt it muſt bee qualified thus for in ſome ſuch ſort, if it be ſubiect to the eye of man. I grant he hath ſeene ſome particular perſons that belong vnto the Church, and are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof (and ſo haue I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) but for the Church it ſelfe, whoſe formality conſiſteth in a ſpirituall coniunction with Chriſt the head, &amp; of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers themſelues one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this myſticall vnion I am ſure he did never ſee: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee did never ſee the Church no not any particular Church, to ſpeake properly, much leſſe the <hi>Catholike church.</hi> This <hi>is an article of faith, and not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:240:27"/>an obiect of ſenſe,</hi> farre aboue the ſpheare of all optike learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; it is an Article to bee belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, not a thing to be deſcried, by a paire of ſpectacles, or any other proſpectiue glaſſe; if hee meane <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ideo pro intelligo,</hi> by the old Grammer rule, let him and the reſt ſpeake ſo a Gods name, and call it hereafter the intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible Church, that we may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them: for then they ſhall begin to ſpeake ſomewhat more like Proteſtants: for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, while they call it the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall, yet viſible Church, they interfeare at every word, and ſpeake pure non-ſenſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Pope not the head of the Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vnder one lawfull viſible head.)</hi> It had beene plaine dealing to haue named the Pope, rather then to vſe ſuch a circumlocuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:240:27"/>of words: for you muſt not doubt but that he is that Viſible head whom he meanes. Now it deſerues a <hi>Quare,</hi> why the Church being but one body, ſhould need two Heads? Why being but one Monarchy it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſiſt without two Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs? To ſay that one is a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the other an inviſible; the one a principall, the other a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall head, it is all one in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as if they told vs of two Chriſts, a viſible and an inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; &amp; perhaps in time to come the world may heare of ſome ſuch matter, if this doctrine goe on. In reaſon they ought to make two Churches; becauſe the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy muſt bee multiplied accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the multiplication of the heads; we are ſure that Chriſt now in heauen, is every way as able to governe his Church by himſelfe, as he was while he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:240:28"/>vpon earth: if in regard of his bodily abſence they thinke it neceſſary that he ſhould leaue ſome deputie behind him: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth this hang well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome other popiſh Poſitions; for by their doctrine Chriſt is not ſo aſcended into heauen, but that they haue his body (as they ſay) remaining ſtill among them vpon earth; and that not only in a ſpirituall manner, but moſt really and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally. They haue freer recourſe to Chriſt now by the helpe of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</note> then they could poſſibly haue with him while he converſed here in the fleſh. Nay they haue not ſo free acceſſe to the Pope I am ſure, as they haue to him, with whom they may ſpeake, when they liſt, vpon every Altar, and in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Pixe. And what folly is it to ſeeke to the foote, when we
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:240:28"/>may goe to the head? To ſet vp a miniſteriall head in the Church, where the principall himſelfe is alwaies at hand? <hi>Dulciùs ex ipſo fonte bibuntur aquae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides,<note place="margin">No viſible head neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</note> if this viſible Head were ſuch a neceſſary imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Church of God as they would make vs beleeue, it ſeemes ſtrange to mee why his name ſhould be forgotten, and that in thoſe very Scriptures, where the Governors, and the government of the <hi>Church</hi> is purpoſely treated of; or how was it poſſible for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of Apoſtles, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Evangeliſts, of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and teachers ordained by Chriſt for the perfecting of the Saints, for the worke of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry. &amp;c. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4 11. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. to forget the name of this Paſtour Paramont: who now takes vpon him to be <hi>Dominus
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:240:29"/>fac totum,</hi> and to rule the roſt throughout all Chriſtendome.</p>
               <p>There is another thing that makes mee doubt much of this matter, namely that whereas the Church hath ſtill bin known by the name of a Monarchy, yet the Pope among all other his ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles hath not ordinarily taken vpon him the name of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, till of late. I know ſome ſuch thing hath beene mutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a pretty while in the Schooles: but it never paſt for currant Doctrine in the Church till within theſe few yeares: nay, it is not ſo farre paſt yet, but that the Sorboniſts of <hi>Paris,</hi> &amp; generally the whole Church of France, oppoſe ſtrongly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. In like ſort, whereas the Church hath ever beene cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the body of Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.23. yet I never heard of a Pope ſo deſperate that durſt call the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:240:29"/>Church his body: which yet in ſome ſort hee might be allowed to doe, if it bee lawfull for him in any ſort to call himſelfe the Head of the Church (by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Relatiues.)</p>
               <p>Moreover, I finde the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers of this Doctrine much puzzelled in ſeeking to expreſſe what authority it is, that the Pope may challenge in right of his headſhip, and Monarchie, &amp; what power is appendant to that name: whether it bee a meere ſpirituall power, or a temporall, or both, or ſome third mixt power compounded of temporall and ſpirituall?<note place="margin">Difference betweene the Papiſts touching the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and the ſpirituall power of the Pope.</note> Here I ſee them at ſuch deadly ſtrife among themſelues, as I hold it no ſafe truſting either of them, vntill I ſhall firſt finde that they truſt one another better. Card. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe within theſe few yeares knew not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:240:30"/>what to make of that matter, as it appeareth by his latter writings compared with the former.</p>
               <p>When he firſt ſet forth his bookes of controuerſies, he was of one opinion concerning this point, which afterward hee changed &amp; became of another, as you ſhall finde by his recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, wherein hee did not mend that which was amiſſe, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did in his <hi>Retractati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> but <hi>proficiens in peius,</hi> like thoſe, of whom the Apoſtle ſpeakes, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13. hee made that worſe which was too bad before; euen in the iudgement of his owne good friends. In his former writings of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though hee had pleaded for the Papall authority, <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum honeſtè potuit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Barclay. Sixtus Quintus.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; plus eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am quàm debuit:</hi> ſaith <hi>William Barclay</hi> a Papiſt, yet was <hi>Sixtus
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:240:30"/>Quintus</hi> the Pope ſo diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his booke, that he was once of the mind, to haue dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all his writings, becauſe he did not ſpeake home to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe contentment: I meane, becauſe hee did not attribute ſuch an vnlimited, and tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent power vnto him, as that proud &amp; imperious Praelate did challenge in right of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Monarchie; becauſe hee did not affirme him to haue as direct a temporall power over Kings, as a ſpirituall over Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, making all Kingdomes, as well as all Churches, ſubiect to his diſpoſition. See <hi>Barclay de poteſtate Papae in Principes christianos, cap.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>They that contract the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Pope within the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of a meere Spirituall iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, though they ſpeake more modeſtly then other of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:240:31"/>their fellowes; yet in as much as they extend this iuriſdiction over the whole world, (which in reſpect of him they make to bee but as one Dioceſſe) even this Paradox of theirs is as falſe as the others, though not ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent: &amp; as iniurious to Chriſt and his Church, though it be not ſo pragmatically dangerous to ſecular ſtates, and Princes Crownes: for if the Spirituall Kingdome of Chriſt bee of no greater extent then the Popes iuriſdiction, it followeth that none are Chriſtians but Papiſts; which though ſome Popiſh Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritane in his fiery zeale, will make no bones perhaps to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme: yet all of them are not ſo deſperate, and hee that ſpeakes ſo in his heat, muſt recall it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in cold blood, or elſe hee will leaue Chriſt but a poore Kingdome, and a few ſubiects
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:240:31"/>in reſpect of that multitude, which God promiſed vnto him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.8. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. <hi>v.</hi> 8.9. &amp;c. Nay how ſhall that Prophecy of <hi>Malachy</hi> bee verified of the Church, ſpreading it ſelfe from the riſing of the Sunne to the going downe thereof, if there bee no more Chriſtians in the world then there be Papiſts? All the world knowes that the Popes Kingdome never exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it ſelfe ſo farre, as that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy ſpeakes of, by many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, when it was at the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt. And Papiſts haue little hope ever to ſee it hereafter ſpread over the whole World. Now becauſe the Pope hath no juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in thoſe parts, nor ever had, ſhall wee thinke therefore that Chriſt hath no kingdome there? Or that the <hi>Grecian, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menian, Jndian, Aethiopian,</hi> and other <hi>African</hi> Churches bee no
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:240:32"/>Churches at all, becauſe they are no Popiſh Churches? (I omit to ſpeake here of Proteſtants in <hi>Europe,</hi> whoſe multitude the Pope knowes better then hee loues.) But for thoſe other which I was ſpeaking of, it is certaine that either the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies mentioned before are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed in thoſe Chriſtians, or elſe they were never accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed hitherunto at all: eyther <hi>Chriſt</hi> now reigneth in thoſe Churches, or elſe his kingdome was never ſo large as it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that it ſhould be. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it cannot be denied, but that thoſe Eaſterne &amp; Southerne Chriſtians are much degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from their primitiue purity, and there bee diverſe things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in their profeſſion; yet, they are Chriſtians ſtill: and whoſoever denies them that name, becauſe they are none of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:240:32"/>the Popes creatures, hee robs Chriſt of more ſubiects then hee leaues him to raigne over. <hi>Vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> timetur, &amp; laudatur Deus, ibi vera eſt Eccleſia Auguſt. in Pſal.</hi> 21.</p>
               <p>The Church for the ſpace of ſixe hundred yeares was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without this viſible head, but ſo farre from deſiring it, that when <hi>Iohn</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> an ambitious Prelate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to affect this matter, he was told by <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Great that his courſe was Antichriſtian: &amp; yet it is certaine the ambition of this Patriarch was no more, then that which hath ſince bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken forth in ambitious Popes, vnder the name of their Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy: and the ſame reaſons which <hi>Gregory</hi> vſed againſt <hi>Iohn,</hi> being many in number, they conclude as ſtrongly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Gregories</hi> Succeſſors now
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:240:33"/>a daies, as ever they did then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the other. Read <hi>Greg.</hi> on that <hi>Argument, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 30.32.36. <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi> If the ſame queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were made now to the Pope, which was then made by <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> to that Patriarch. <hi>Tu quid Chriſto vniverſalis Eccleſiae ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piti in extremi iudicij dicturus es examine, qui cuncta eius membra vibi conaris vniverſalis appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ſupponere?</hi> I thinke his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe would be to ſeeke of an anſwere. I am ſure <hi>Gerſon</hi> a learned Roman Catholike, was ſo farre from thinking ſuch a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Head to bee any matter of neceſſity in the <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> that hee thought the body might doe well enough though this head were taken off from the ſhoulders: as appeares by his booke written, <hi>De aufe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibilitate Papae.</hi> And ſo I paſſe from this deſcription of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:240:33"/>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All that followes from thence to the end almoſt of the firſt page might well haue bin ſpared, neither can I deviſe to what purpoſe it is brought in.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That our Saviour Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Prieſt for ever</hi> ſecundum ordinem Melchiſedec,<note place="margin">Chriſt the head of the Church.</note> 
                  <hi>was the firſt viſible Head and founder of the ſaid holy Christian Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, &amp;c.</hi>— Hee is no Chriſtian that doubts of it: but when I heare him ſay, that Chriſt <hi>(was the firſt viſible head of the Church)</hi> me thinkes hee ſpeakes ſtrangely, vnleſſE hee thinke that Chriſt is now ceaſed to bee ſomewhat that hee was heretofore. For why elſe did he not ſay in <hi>praeſenti,</hi> that Chriſt is the head of the Church, as well as <hi>(he is a prieſt for ever)</hi> vnleſſe he were afraid to hurt the Popes
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:240:34"/>head? <hi>Primus ſemper dicitur in ordine ad ſecundum, &amp; ſecundus ad tertium.</hi> Now if the Church by the death of Chriſt her firſt head got her a ſecond head, which was S. <hi>Peter,</hi> why then vpon his death ſhee got a third head, and ſo conſequently hath had as many Heads, as ſhee hath had Popes, which is ſcarce good Engliſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> How farre the Clergy are to bee obeyed.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Chriſt did institute a Clergy &amp; a Laity in his Church, the one to preach and adminiſter Sacraments, the other to learne and to obey, &amp;c.</hi>— I hope hee doth not meane that the Clergy are freed from obeying the Goſpell, becauſe they are bound to preach it; But that Chriſt did inſtitute ſuch a diſtinction of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:240:34"/>people in his Church we know before hee told vs ſo. Heere a man might ſuſpect that ſome Prieſt had his finger in the fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this writing, in as much as when he ſpeakes of the duty of the Laity, he tels them, <hi>(That they are bound to obey the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in all things touching their Faith,—)</hi> a ſpeech too lauiſh for any Prieſt to ſpeake, and too ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh for any ingenuous Lay man to heare, except it be much cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, <hi>(they muſt obey in all things)</hi> he meanes firſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, then the doctrine. <hi>Ex per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonis fidem, non ex fide perſonas.</hi> And <hi>Champnies,</hi> an Engliſh <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boniſt,</hi> profeſſeth as much, <hi>l. de vocat. miniſt, c.</hi> 1. And ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Stapleton; In doctrinâ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis non quid dicatur, ſed quis loquatur attendendum eſt. defenſ. Eccleſiaſticae autorit. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp; demon ſtrat. princip. doctrin. l.</hi> 10.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:240:35"/>
                  <hi>c.</hi> 5. Which <hi>Tertullian</hi> thought a great abſurdity, and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes it, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritas docendo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuadet, non ſuadendo docet: ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Valent. Hic eſt ſacerdos de genere Aaronis, non decipiet nos.</hi> 1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 7.14. ſo did ſome over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulous <hi>Iews</hi> ſay of <hi>Alcimus;</hi> but yet they were deceiued. And ſo would your <hi>friend</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you, to belieue him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is a Romiſh Prieſt, and to take vp your faith vpon his credit. But let it firſt appeare, that their Clergy are ſo privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by ſpeciall or common grace, that either they cannot preach falſe doctrine, though they would, or that they wil not though they can, &amp; then we are content <hi>they ſhould bee obeyed in all things. Alfonſus à Caſtro</hi> tells indeed ſtrange things that hee heard a <hi>Dominican</hi> preach con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the priviledges of his owne order. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de haereſ. c.</hi> 9. but
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:240:35"/>your <hi>friend</hi> goes beyond him, and ſaies as much of every po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſt, ſuch <hi>muſt bee obeyed in all things,</hi> and therefore ſuch cannot, or ſhould not erre; and then <hi>vbi Papae infallibilitas?</hi> what preheminence ſhall his holineſſe haue more then every common Maſſe Prieſt? Either this <hi>Pontifex maximus</hi> this high Prieſt muſt forbeare to ſay his <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> or forbid other Prieſts to ſay theirs, or elſe they will goe cheeke by cheeke with him: <hi>ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſufficit dicere;</hi> neither can they ſay, that they are all equall <hi>poteſtate ordinis</hi> only: for they will be ſo <hi>poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te iuriſdictionis</hi> too, if they are to be <hi>obeyed in all things.</hi> What will they ſay then? that the Pope alone is the infallible Church to the learned Papiſt; but to the common people eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pariſh Prieſt is their Church:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:240:36"/>to this I may anſwere, that as <hi>Cotton</hi> ſeem'd to miſtruſt even the Popes infallibility, when he deſired to know of the divell the ſtrongeſt proofe in Scripture for Purgatory, <hi>Thuan. To.</hi> 5. <hi>fol.</hi> 1136. (though hee needed not haue troubled the divell ſo farre, when many of his owne friends can aſſure him, that there is no proofe of it there) ſo haue wee alſo juſt cauſe to miſtruſt the inferior Prieſts the feet, when the head begins to faile; and when we heare S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> crying out, that all hereſies and commotions both Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall and Civill commonly came from Prieſts: nay, it ſeemes, they juſtly deſerue to be thus ſtigmatized, when their owne <hi>Canons</hi> haue laid this note vpon them, which ſaies, <hi>omne malum à Sacerdotibus: diſt.</hi> 50. <hi>quod retentum à Gregorio,</hi> 13.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:240:36"/>
                  <hi>expunxit Sixtus Quintus Jnd. expurg. Belg. fol,</hi> 306.</p>
               <p>Beſides by this rule of blind obedience, they that followed <hi>Luthers</hi> doctrine are juſtified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pope, becauſe he was their lawfull Paſtor: and they did no more then their duty in harkening vnto him; if it be true indeede that the <hi>Laity are bound to obey the Clergy in all things touching their faith and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The perpetuity of Chriſts Church on earth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Church increaſed by Preaching and Miracles at the firſt; That it ſhall continue vnto the end of the world by vertue of Chriſts promiſe and the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All this is vndoubted truth, and I pray you aske your <hi>friend,</hi> whether hee know any Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:240:37"/>that doth deny it? <hi>Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> &amp; ſome other of the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe crew haue gone about to perſwade the world, that wee beleeue not the perpetuity of Chriſts Church for ever vpon earth; but it is ſo ſhameleſſe a ſlaunder, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſtands vpon our defence, and pleads our cauſe againſt all ſuch calumniators. <hi>Notandum eſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>multos ex noſtris tempus terere:</hi> &amp; let your <hi>friend</hi> note it (for hee is one of thoſe <hi>multi</hi> whom it concernes) <hi>dum probant abſolutè Eccleſiam non poſſe deficere. Nam Calvinus &amp; caeteri Haeretici id concedunt. Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Eccl. milit. c.</hi> 13. <hi>in initio capit.</hi> And though him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vndertaking in the ſame place to ſet downe the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants opinion, doe it very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>towardly, yet you ſee what hee thinkes of thoſe other game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:240:37"/>who charge vs to hold that the Church hath at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time decayed, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that Chriſt hath failed in his promiſe made vnto her, <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus terunt</hi> (ſaith he) they are all but triflers. If your <hi>friend</hi> haue any ſuch conce it of vs, deſire him to belieue <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and hereafter to haue a better opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If not, aske him to what purpoſe hee cited <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.22. <hi>Math.</hi> 28.19.20. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.16.17. <hi>Math.</hi> 18.18? Howſoever let him now know that we belieue the Catholique Church to bee <hi>Regnum quod non diſſipabitur,</hi> an everlaſting Kingdome that ſhall ſtand when all earthly Kingdomes faile. But wee doe not beleeue that this is true of every particular Church, and wee know that the Romiſh Church is no more then a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and therefore as ſubiect
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:240:38"/>to mutability and corruption, as any other of the ſame nature. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, tell him how wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that the holy Ghoſt doth, and ever will guide the ſame <hi>Catholique Church</hi> into all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary truth: but we deny firſt that all thoſe things are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be beleeved, which Rome profeſſeth as truths. Secondly that the guidance into ſuch truths is a grace entailed to any one ſucceſſion of Biſhops more then to other, or that the Popes chaire hath any greater reaſon to preſume of her infallibility, then any other Patriarchicall Seas had heretofore of theirs. But we muſt talke more of this hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Saint Peter not the miniſteriall head of the Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That our Saviour did conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peter to bee Miniſteriall
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:240:38"/>of his Church—)</hi> Well may the name of a Miniſteriall head be given to Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in reſpect of his Apoſtleſhip, and there is not one of the twelue, but that in the ſame reſpect, the ſame name belongs vnto him; as they are called the twelue foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the holy Ieruſalem, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.14. ſo they may bee called 12. Miniſteriall Heads of the Church vnder Chriſt. But to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate theſe names vnto <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> alone, to make him not a Miniſteriall, but the Miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all head, as if the reſt were no Heads at all, it is ſuch a wrong done to the other Apoſtles, as cruell Landlords ſometimes of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to their Tenants, when they take away their common from them, and make it their owne incloſure. As for the curteſie which perhaps they thinke they doe vnto Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> it is ſuch a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:240:39"/>one as he will never giue them thankes for; that bleſſed Saint knowes well enough, that all this quarrelling about Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is not for his ſake, but for the Popes, and that his name is vſed only for a leaping ſtocke to helpe the other to horſe. Hee takes as much delight in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable ſupremacy, which they would caſt vpon him, joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the diſgrace of his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Apoſtles, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> did when the men of <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra</hi> would haue ſacrificed vnto them, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.14. <hi>Hoc erant vti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; caeteri Apoſtoli, quod fuit Petrus, pari conſortio praediti &amp; Honoris &amp; Poteſtatis: Cip. de vnit. Eccleſ.</hi> And yet we doe not ſay that this equality betweene the Apoſtles was ſo equall, but that there was ever a <hi>Prius &amp; Poſterius</hi> among them, as in all well-guided ſocieties it is fit
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:240:39"/>there ſhould bee, for avoiding confuſion; <hi>Iames,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> are termed Pillars, by which they are vnderſtood to be perſons of ſpeciall note a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.9. and like enough that <hi>Peter,</hi> in regard ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his ſeniority in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip, or the fervency of his zeale to Chriſt, or ſome other ſpeciall grace, wherein hee did excell, might be a more eminent pillar then any one of the other; <hi>vt Plato Princeps Philoſophorum, ſic Petrus Princeps Apoſtolorum. Hierom. adverſus Pelag. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. Now as that name made not other Philoſophers ſubiect to <hi>Plato,</hi> ſo neither doth the like giuen to <hi>Peter</hi> inferre any Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction that hee had over his fellowes, or makes them any whit inferiour vnto him that way. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith of <hi>Paul,</hi> that he was not inferiour
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:240:40"/>to <hi>Peter,</hi> or to any other of the Apoſtles that went before one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in time in 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. And in his booke <hi>de Incar. Dom. Cap.</hi> 4. ſpeaking of that Primacy that <hi>Peter</hi> had, he calleth it <hi>Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Confeſſionis,</hi> wherein <hi>Peter</hi> was preferred; a primacy of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, faith he, not of honour, a primacy of faith, but not of degree. Your <hi>friend</hi> is of another minde, and brings Scripture to proue a greater ſupremacy gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vnto <hi>Peter</hi> then all this we ſpeake of, conſider his proofes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  </hi> Peters ſupremacy.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I ſay to thee, thou art Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and vpon this rocke will I build my Church, and the gates of Hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it; and J will giue to thee the keyes of the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and whatſoever thou ſhalt bind vpon earth, it ſhall be bound
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:240:40"/>alſo in the heavens: and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thou ſhalt looſe in earth, it ſhall be looſed alſo in the heavens, Math.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.19.) Before that ever our Saviour ſpake theſe words to <hi>Peter,</hi> you muſt vnderſtand that hee had propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a certaine queſtion to them all in generall. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>os autem quem me eſſe dicitis, v.</hi> 15. Vnto which queſtion <hi>Peter</hi> making anſwere in the name of them all, ſaith. <hi>Tues ille filius Dei viuentis, verſ.</hi> 16. Wherevpon hee receiued the promiſe of the keyes, and thoſe other comfortable words ſpoken by Chriſt vnto him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.19. yet not ſo ſpoken to him alone, but that it is apparent that the ſubſtance of the promiſe did equally belong vnto them all: and there is nothing ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belonging vnto <hi>Peter</hi> alone throughout the whole ſpeech, but only an alluſion betweene
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:240:41"/>his name and the nature of his confeſſion, betweene <hi>Petrus</hi> &amp; <hi>Petra;</hi> for the reſt, it is all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, for either wee muſt ſay that the diſciples did make no anſwere at all to their Maſters queſtion, which had beene a point of great incivility, and ſo not likely; or elſe the anſwer that <hi>Peter</hi> made muſt bee taken for their common anſwer, and his confeſſion the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of them all. Now if it be granted that it was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon confeſſion, and only deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by Peter as the <hi>fore-man of the Jury,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> lib. <hi>2.</hi> Hiſt. Eccl. cap. <hi>14.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> (for ſo <hi>Euſebius</hi> calls him) our Saviours-reply therevnto cannot with any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity be otherwiſe vnderſtood then to belong vnto them all, though ſpoken vnto Peter; as judges vſe to direct their ſpeech to the foreman, when they would haue the whole Iury
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:240:41"/>take knowledge of it: <hi>Petrus pro omnibus dixit, &amp; cum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus accepit, Orig. tract.</hi> 1. <hi>in Mat. &amp; Aug. de verbis Dom. ſecund. Mat. Ser.</hi> 13. <hi>Quia tu dixiſti mihi, Tu es filius Dei vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui, &amp; ego tibi, tu es Petrus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vpon this rocke will I build my Church-).</hi> Whether by the rocke wee vnderſtand Chriſt himſelfe, or whether wee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the confeſſion of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> made of Chriſt, all comes to one; if there be any difference betweene them it is meerely verball, and conſiſteth rather of a diverſe manner of mens ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing their mindes, then in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny matter of ſubſtance. But for the perſon of <hi>Peter,</hi> the Church of Chriſt did never vnderſtand her ſelfe to bee any otherwiſe built vpon it, then vpon the reſt of the Apoſtles; <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.14. or then Saint <hi>Paul</hi> when hee ſaith,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:240:42"/>it is built vpon the foundation not only of the Apoſtles, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Prophets, that is vpon their doctrine.<note place="margin">Eph. 2.20.</note>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Tu es Petrus &amp; ſuper hanc Petram, quam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſus es, ſuper hanc Petram quam cognoviſti, dicens, tu es Chriſtus filius Dei viui, aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabo Eccleſiam meam: ſuper me aedificabo te, non me ſuper te, Aug. vbi ſupra;</hi>
                  </q> I could cite twenty places out of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, beſides <hi>Ambr. Ser.</hi> 84. <hi>Hil. de Trin. l.</hi> 2. <hi>Hier. in Mat. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>Tert. adverſus Marcion. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 13, <hi>Theod. in Pſal.</hi> 47. But for <hi>Auguſt.</hi> he is ſo plain for vs againſt the Popiſh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would faine quarrell with him vpon the point, &amp; chargeth him with ignorance of the Hebrew tongue. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Rom. Pont. c.</hi> 10. and <hi>Stapleton</hi> calls it <hi>lapſum hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum</hi> in that holy Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:240:42"/>he could not thinke of the matter as they would haue him; (<hi>Princip. doctrinal. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the gates of Hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it—)</hi> This makes it more plaine that the other part of the ſpeech was not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, becauſe this cannot bee vnderſtood of <hi>Peter</hi> alone, and ſo <hi>Origen</hi> collecteth <hi>Tr.</hi> 1. <hi>in Mat.</hi> ſhall we dare to ſay (ſaith he) that the gates of Hell ſhall not overcome onely <hi>Peter,</hi> and that the ſame gates ſhall prevaile againſt all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles? And againe in the ſame <hi>Tract.</hi> 1. <hi>in Mat.</hi> If you thinke that the whole Church was builded only vpon <hi>Peter,</hi> what will you ſay of <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſonne of thunder, and of every of the Apoſtles?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I will giue to thee the keyes &amp;c.</hi> Here is nothing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in the Keyes to <hi>Peter,</hi> nor
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:240:43"/>in the power of binding &amp; looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but what is likewiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to all the Apoſtles, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Quaecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ligaveritis in terrâ, erunt ligata &amp; in coelo,</hi> and when this promiſe came to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.22.23. you ſhall finde that it was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to all alike. <hi>Accipite Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Sanctum, quorum remiſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis peccata, remittentur iis.</hi>-Now it is certaine that remitting and retaining of ſins is a power of the ſame extent with the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the keyes, and that being giuen to them all, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20. as well as vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> proues that there was nothing promiſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Peter, Mat.</hi> 16. but was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to them all,
<q>
                     <hi>Cuncti A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtoli claves regni coelorum accipiunt. Hier. adverſus Iovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianum l.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; Origen. An ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro ſoli Petro dantur claves regni coelorum, nec alius beato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:240:43"/>quiſquam eas accepturus eſt? Quod ſi dictum hoc tibi da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo claves,- caeteris quo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune eſt, cur non ſimul omnia communia Tract.</hi> 1. <hi>in Mat. &amp; Cypr. Chriſtus Apoſtolis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus poſt reſurrectionem ſuam parem poteſtatem tribuit l.</hi> 1. <hi>de vnitat. Eccl. &amp; Auguſt. in Ioh. tractat.</hi> 124.— <hi>quando Petro dictum eſt, tibi dabo claves—&amp; quodcun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ligaveris- vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſam ſignificabat eccleſiam vide eundem Tra.</hi> 50. <hi>&amp; The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oph.</hi> vpon <hi>Math.</hi> 16.</q> Nay <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelme</hi> that was a child in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the Fathers, yet hee vnderſtood this truth. <hi>Notan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quod haec po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtas non ſolum Petro data eſt: ſed ſiout Petrus vnus pro omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus respondit, ſic Chriſtus in Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro omnibus hanc poteſtatem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And our Saviour ſaid,</hi> Simon
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:240:44"/>Simon, <hi>behold Satan hath requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to haue thee for to ſift as wheat, but J haue prayed for thee that thy faith faile not, and thou being converted confirme thy brethren, Luk.</hi> 22. <hi>verſ.</hi> 31.32.) The firſt part of this ſpeech was ſpoken to all the Diſciples, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanas expetivit vos vt cribraret:</hi> as the vulgar likewiſe tranſlat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: and therefore it is no good dealing in your <hi>friend</hi> to render it in the ſingular number <hi>(Satan hath required to haue thee for to ſift)</hi> as if theſe words had beene ſpoken to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, which is a meere falſifying of the Text: as if a man would pay his credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor with counterfeit coine; but let that paſſe with his former citation of <hi>Malachy.</hi> In the words themſelues, 1. Chriſt ſignifies to his Diſciples the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of Satan againſt them all, and conſequently the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:240:44"/>they ſtood, vnleſſe his grace did ſtand by them. 2. Becauſe he knew that <hi>Peters</hi> danger was greateſt, &amp; that he would proue the weakeſt in his performance, who had made the greateſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of loue to his Maſter: Chriſt I ſay, foreſeeing that <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> fall would bee more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in many reſpects then the fall of any of his other fellowes, therefore hee turnes the latter part of his ſpeech to him alone, promiſing to aſſiſt him with his ſpeciall prayer, as the greatnes of his ſinne had ſpeeciall need of;
<q>If Satan deſire to ſift them all (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) why did not Chriſt pray for them all? it is evident that to touch <hi>Peter</hi> more deepely and to ſhew his fault to bee more grievous then any of the reſt, Chriſt turned his ſpeech to him in particular, <hi>in Math.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:240:45"/>Hom.</hi> 83. </q> All this proues no greater Monarchy, but rather a greater infirmity in <hi>Peter</hi> then in any of the reſt, and greater mercy in Chriſt towards him, whoſe ſinne did deſerue à grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iudgement. As S. <hi>Paul</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferres the like of himſele 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16. I am ſure the Pope will not bee thought to ſucceed <hi>Peter</hi> in the ſinne of his deniall: why then doth hee claime the benefit of Chriſts prayer, <hi>Ego pro te oravi,-</hi> which was made purpoſely for <hi>Peter</hi> in regard of that ſinne? For as <hi>Peters</hi> deniall was his perſonall fault, and is not derived <hi>per traducem</hi> to his Succeſſors, (for then not only many Popes ſhould <hi>Apoſtatare,</hi> as <hi>Lyra</hi> in <hi>Math.</hi> 16. ſaith, but all Popes ſhould be Renegates which I beleeue not.) As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was a perſonall ſinne in <hi>Peter</hi> to deny Chriſt, ſo the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:240:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>prayer of Chriſt for <hi>Peter</hi> was a perſonall favour beſtowed vpon him: and the Pope hath no more right to the one then the other; beſides, let it bee conſidered, that the faith which Saint <hi>Peter</hi> obtained by Chriſts prayer was not only <hi>fides notitiae,</hi> ſuch as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels haue and tremble, but it was <hi>fides fiduciae vera &amp; ſalvifica ſides:</hi> ſuch a faith as worketh with charity, and whoſoever hath it ſhall vndoubtedly be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; and ſo <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands it, <hi>Oraui proute ne defice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret fides tua, hoc eſt, ne in fine pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reas, Hom.</hi> 72. <hi>in Ioh.</hi> Now it is confeſſed by all Papiſts, that all Popes are not furniſhed with this kinde of faith. Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> 6. is ſaid to haue doubted of the ſalvation of many of his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors: and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (if the Seminary Prieſt bely him not) hath paſſed a peremptory iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:240:46"/>vpon Pope <hi>Sixtus Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. Quia ſine poenitentiâ vixit, &amp; ſine poenitentiâ mortuus eſt, quantum ſapio, quantum capio deſcendit ad inferos. Watſon</hi> in his <hi>Quodlibets.</hi> Now if this be true, that Popes may bee dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it muſt needs follow, that either Chriſts prayer did not prevaile with God, (which were impiety to thinke) or that the Pope was never thought vpon by Chriſt, when this pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was a making. Now to his third proofe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>3.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Saviour Chriſt asking</hi> Peter <hi>îf he loved him more then theſe, ſaid yea Lord, thou knowſt J loue thee: wherevpon Chriſt ſaid to him twice, feed my Lambes, and the third time feed my ſheepe, Ioh.</hi> 21. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16.17.) Here is ſome miſtaking of the Text againe: for Chriſt did not
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:240:46"/>ſay twice to <hi>Peter</hi> feed my Lambs, &amp; once feede my ſheep: but twice feed my Sheepe, and once feed my Lambs. But let this paſſe for a <hi>peccadillo.</hi> I ſay farther, that in the words there is nothing ſpoken more to <hi>Peter,</hi> then is elſewhere ſpoken to all the Apoſtles: <hi>When they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to goe, and teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions baptizing them,</hi> Mat. 28.19.20. And if hee thinke that there lies any ſpeciall myſtery in theſe words, becauſe there is ſuch diſtinct mention of lambs, and ſheepe both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <hi>Peters</hi> charge, the like whereof we doe not find in the miſſion of the other Apoſtles: Let him not be too haſty to ſay ſo, till hee haue conſidered the words of their generall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Goe into all the world</hi> (Saint <hi>Peter</hi> could not haue a larger Dioces) <hi>and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:240:47"/>preach the Gospell to every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> Therefore whether they be Lambes or ſheepe, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the charge of euery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtle as well as to Saint <hi>Peters.</hi> But they will ſay that <hi>Peter</hi> is commanded not only <hi>Paſcere,</hi> but <hi>regere:</hi> and that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies more then a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall duty, even a kinde of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall authority to bee given by Chriſt vnto him. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſtands much vpon the word though there bee little cauſe. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Rom. Pont. c.</hi> 15. I know that Kings are ſometimes called Shepheards, as <hi>Homer</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Nay God himſelfe cals <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſo, <hi>Jſa.</hi> 44.28. But I thinke it were harſh, becauſe Kings are ſometimes called ſhepheards, to infer that Shepheards there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are Kings, whether wee ſpeake of ruſtike or Eccleſiaſtick Shepheards.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:240:47"/>But if <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> bee ſuch a myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call word, and doth imply ſuch a ſoveraigne authority, what meant Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to vſe that word ſpeaking to the ordinary Presbyters of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> whom he willed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28.</p>
               <p>You haue heard his three texts of Scriptures: which if they be ſo cleere for the ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, as hee would haue you thinke: let him giue you ſome reaſon why Pope <hi>Zozimus, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifacius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Caeleſtinus,</hi> did not alledge any of theſe Scriptures in the 6. Councell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> when their ſupremacy lay a bleeding, but only made their claime by the Councell of <hi>Nice.</hi> it is not likely that ever ſuch learned and wiſe Prelates as they, would haue ſought for hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane proofes to iuſtify their cauſe, if they had knowne how
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:240:48"/>to doe it by divine authority: which is to mee an vndoubted argument that theſe fore-al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged places (<hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.31. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21.16.) either were not thought on in thoſe daies to imply any ſuch Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie in <hi>Peter:</hi> or that <hi>Peters</hi> ſupremacy (whatſoever it bee) was not thought to belong any whit to the Pope. Elſe why did they not ſtand vpon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? Why did the Popes Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates vrge the <hi>Nicene</hi> Canon? Or rather why did they forge it to ſerue their turnes? for ſo it is certaine that they did, and the forgery remaines vpon record in the Acts of the Councell. And though <hi>Cardinall Baron. Tom.</hi> 5. <hi>Annal</hi> haue ſtrained his wits hard to ſalue the matter, yet it will not be.— <hi>Haeret lateri le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalis arundo.</hi> But as I was about to ſay: if theſe Scriptures make
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:240:48"/>any good proofe for the Popes Supremacy, why were not they brought forth in that Councell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> either by the Pope or his Legates, rather then the <hi>Nicene</hi> Canon? Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was one of the Fathers preſent in that <hi>Carthagenian</hi> Councell, when this cauſe was debated, and is it likely that either the Pope would haue ſtood then vpon Canons, if he had known any Canonicall ſcripture for it, or that Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and the reſt would haue denied him any authority that was due to him by Gods word? I conclude that either the Church in thoſe daies did not vnderſtand theſe places of Scripture, or the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh doth not vnderſtand them now. But ſee whether theſe proofes that follow doe helpe his cauſe any better.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:240:49"/>
               <head>1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>When all the holy Apoſtles are named,</hi> S. <hi>Peter is the firſt, Mat.</hi> 10.2.-) That is not ſo: for Saint <hi>Andrew</hi> is named before him, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.44. <hi>James</hi> is named be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos</hi> were both named before him, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. Nay ſee 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.5. and <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.7. and you ſhall finde him named laſt of them all. 2. If it were ſo that <hi>Peter</hi> were ſtill firſt named, yet what a weake foundation is that, for ſo great a building as they would raiſe vpon it? The moſt that can be inferred there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon is a primacy of order which no man ever denied. If that will content the Pope when a generall ſcrutinie of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops is called, to haue his name ſet in the firſt place, let him take it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:240:49"/>
               <head>2.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>After the Apoſtles had viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly receiued the Holy Ghoſt, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peter made the firſt Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: whereat</hi> 3000. <hi>perſons were converted Act.</hi> 2.4.) For <hi>Peter</hi> to haue his name placed firſt, or to preach the firſt Sermon, theſe are poore proofes for a Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, and it is but a poore Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy that can bee drawne from ſuch proofes. Why ſhould it argue any Supremacy more in him that hee preached the firſt Sermon, then in <hi>Mary Magdaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> that ſhee publiſhed the firſt newes of Chriſts reſurrection to the Diſciples, even to <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe? <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.7. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.2.</p>
               <p>But how if <hi>Peter</hi> did not preach the firſt Sermon after the viſible deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt? Why then all that hee vrgeth is to little purpoſe. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:240:50"/>the text well, Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſermon begins at the 14. <hi>Verſe</hi> of the 2. Chap. of the <hi>Acts:</hi> the effect thereof was the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of 3000. ſoules mentioned <hi>verſ.</hi> 41. It is plaine in the 4. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> that all the Apoſtles had ſpoken publikely to the people, before <hi>Peter</hi> ſtood vp to begin his Sermon. The argument whereof they intreated, was the ſame that <hi>Peter</hi> handled. they declared vnto them <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalia Dei,</hi> the wonderfull works of God, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11. and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> declared nothing elſe. That preaching of theirs was not without good effect, as well as <hi>S. Peters,</hi> though we know not the iuſt number of the converts. Nay it ſeemes that the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thoſe 3000. was the fruit of all their preaching at that time, and not of <hi>Peters</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and ſo it is ſaid <hi>verſ.</hi> 41.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:240:50"/>
                  <hi>That vpon the ſame day were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto the Church about</hi> 3000 <hi>ſoules:</hi> Hee doth not ſay that all this was the effect of <hi>Peters</hi> one ſermon: but that ſo many were converted vpon <hi>that day.</hi> To the next proofe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>With his word and power hee killed Ananias and Saphira for their Sacriledge, Act.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.) It was for their lying to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt that <hi>Peter</hi> ſlew them (and ſo he tells them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.4.) &amp; ſo not for ſacriledge alone. But let it be as hee would haue it. I ſay it proues not that for which he brings it. <hi>S. Paul</hi> by the like power ſmote <hi>Elimas</hi> the Sorcerer with blindneſſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. Now if at the ſame time <hi>Paul</hi> had ſlaine <hi>Elimas</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and in ſtead of taking his eye-ſight from him, had taken away his life (as I thinke no
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:240:51"/>man doubts but hee could haue done) aske your <hi>friend,</hi> whether he thinke that ſuch an act would haue made <hi>Paul</hi> head of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles? Let him ſpit and ſpeake out plainely. His fourth proofe followeth with ſome more ſhew, though of as little force as the former.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>4.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>St Peter called the firſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the Apoſtles holden at Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem and firſt ſpake therein: Act.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Bellar. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Rom. Pont. c.</hi> 22. ſaith, <hi>Petrus in conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio primus loquitur: &amp; ſententi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am eius Jacobus omneſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> alij ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur.</hi> This is more then hee ſhould haue ſaid, becauſe it is more then he can proue: but yet he durſt not ſay as your <hi>friend</hi> doth, that <hi>Peter</hi> called the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell (he knew it to bee vntrue) and if you read the whole <hi>Chap.</hi> you ſhall not find one word to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:240:51"/>that purpoſe. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake firſt in the Councell, ſo <hi>Bellarm.</hi> ſaith indeed: and your <hi>friend</hi> ſpeakes it vpon his credit. But yet the Councell it ſelfe ſaies no. <hi>Act.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 7. When there had beene much diſputing <hi>Peter</hi> roſe vp, and ſaid; <hi>Men and Brethren,</hi>—Therefore ſome other there ſpake of the matter before <hi>Peter.</hi> And what if hee had beene the firſt ſpeaker in that Councell? would that proue his ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? Iuſt as it was proued before by his making the firſt ſermon? Nay rather it is an argument that doth overthrow his ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy altogether. For it is well knowne that in ſuch kinde of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies the inferiour doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſpeake firſt, and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of the Councell hauing heard and gathered their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons deliuereth his iudgement laſt of all, according whereunto
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:240:52"/>the decree commonly paſſeth. So I haue heard that the <hi>Lord Chancelour</hi> doth in the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> and the chiefe Iudges vpon other benches. And in this very Councell of Ieruſalem, when <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> had ſpoken their minds concerning the matter in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Iames</hi> ſtands vp and vſing a ſpeciall kinde of authority, <hi>Men and brethren harken vnto me, v.</hi> 13.—he concludes the buſines: which ſhewes that he, and none but hee was Preſident in that Councell: and ſo <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> tearmes him, calling his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence the definitiue ſentence, according whereunto the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre of the councell was framed, <hi>Chryſoſtom. Hom.</hi> 33. <hi>in Act. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is affirmed by old writers, and ſome moderne learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:240:52"/>that S. Peter was</hi> 25. <hi>yeeres Biſhop of Rome, and by the auncient Eccleſiaſticall wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that Saint Peter and S. Paul were both of them martyred toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Rome vnder the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Nero. Origen. apud Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Euſeb. c.</hi> 24. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>Hiſt. Eccl. Tert. depraeſcrip. c.</hi> 36. <hi>Aug. Tract.</hi> 123 <hi>in Ioh. Chyſoſtom &amp; Beda in hunc locum, S. Ambr. Ser.</hi> 66.68, <hi>S. Maximus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">How Saint Peter was Biſhop of Rome.</note> When <hi>Peter</hi> is called Biſhop of Rome, or <hi>Iames</hi> of Ieruſalem or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtle of any other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular City, we muſt vnderſtand that in thoſe ſpeeches, the name of Biſhop is taken in a larger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, then the ſtrict Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticke vſe of the word will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. As when Presbiters are called Biſhops, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. And the Apoſtleſhip it ſelfe is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 12.25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.13. For as in propriety of ſpeech
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:240:53"/>a Deacon is inferiour to a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biter, &amp; a Presbiter to a Biſhop: ſo is a Biſhop vnto an Apoſtle by many degrees, though the names be often vſed promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly; the calling of the one is extraordinary, and the whole world is within the compaſſe of his commiſſion: the other is a meere ordinary vocation, and his Iuriſdiction confined within the limits of one Dioceſſe. But becauſe the Apoſtles, being ſent by Chriſt to preach the Goſpell to all nations, made their chiefe abode in Citties of greateſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, as <hi>Jeruſalem, Antioch, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus, Rome,</hi>-hence it comes to paſſe that they are often cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Biſhops of thoſe Citties, not in that ſenſe that in times ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the chiefe paſtors of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Citty were knowne by that name of Biſhops, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a more large, or rather licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:240:53"/>vſe of the words: &amp; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever calls S. <hi>Peter</hi> Biſhop of Rome in any other ſenſe then ſo, he ſpeakes as wiſely as if he ſhould ſay, the King of England were Conſtable of New-mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, becauſe his Maieſty reſides often in that place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>How long Saint Peter ſate Biſhop there.</head>
               <p>You vnderſtand by this, that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> is called ſome-times Biſhop of Rome, your <hi>friend</hi> adds, <hi>that hee ſate Biſhop there</hi> 25. <hi>reeres as old writers aſſirme, and ſome moderne learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</hi>-) <hi>Euſebius</hi> indeed ſaith ſo in his Chronicle, and withall that he ſate 7. yeare before hee came to Rome at Antioch: both which cannot poſſibly be true, and is evidently contradicted by the hiſtory of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Galath.</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:240:54"/>as <hi>Onuph.</hi> a learned Papiſt prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in his <hi>Annot.</hi> vpon <hi>Platina de vit. Pont. Rom.</hi> I will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into that diſcours, but deſire you to read what others haue written. I thinke there bee few learned Papiſts now but thinke, that <hi>Euſebius</hi> was deceiued in that point of his Chronicle, or elſe they muſt thinke that Saint <hi>Luke</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. But it is generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed that hee was firſt Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> before hee was Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> Now deſire your <hi>friend</hi> to giue you ſome reaſon why the prerogatiue of <hi>Peters</hi> Supremacy (if there were any ſuch thing in <hi>rerum naturâ</hi>) why it ſhould not belong vnto the Patriarch of <hi>Antioch,</hi> as well as to the Pope of Rome, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſucceſſors alike in their ſeverall places. Perhaps he will ſay becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> was put to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:240:54"/>death in Rome, and not in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch: and to that purpoſe it is likely that he cited <hi>Tertullian. statu foelix Eccleſia, cui totam doctrinam Apoſtolicum ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſuo profuderunt, vbi Petrus paſſioni 'Dominicae adaequatur, vbi Paulus Iohannis exitu coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur, Tert. de praeſcrip. c.</hi> 36. For elſe I know not what thoſe words doe there; but if that be his meaning he might well haue ſpared that quotation; for if S. <hi>Peters</hi> Martyrdome at Rome be a good plea for the ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of that Sea aboue Antioch; why ſhould not Ieruſalem claime it from them both, ſeeing Chriſt the Son of God and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the world was put to death there?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peters ſucceſſors.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> S. <hi>Peters Succeſſors Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome, haue exerciſed
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:240:55"/>chiefe authority in the Church militant ever ſince to this day.</hi>-) And how doth hee proue this. 1. Becauſe that after the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome of S. <hi>Peter</hi> 32. of the ſucceeding Biſhops were like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Martyred. This piece of his reading in old hiſtory might ſerue for ſome vſe in another place, but I cannot ſee how it helpes to proue that Popes haue ever exerciſed chiefe authority in the Church, to which end it is brought here in this place. I am ſure that Popes in theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ages haue neither ſucceeded <hi>Peter</hi> in his Martyrdome, nor deſire to be his succeſſors that way. All the world ſees they haue beene more buſy in make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Martyrs, then in ſuffering of Martyrdome; and in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect may better bee called the Succeſſors of <hi>Nero, Decius,</hi> and <hi>Diocleſian:</hi> then of <hi>S. Peter</hi> and thoſe
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:240:55"/>32. holy Biſhops that ſucceeded him. It is certaine that by the cruelty of Popes, and their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh inſtruments there hath beene more Chriſtian blood ſhed in the world, then ever was ſhed by thoſe heathen ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants in the greateſt heat of their perſecuting. What though the Pope ſucceeded in place to thoſe 32. holy Biſhops and Martyrs: It is no otherwiſe then as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption ſucceedeth generation, vinegar ſucceedeth wine, as the Turke ſucceedeth <hi>Iames</hi> in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, and other of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in other places.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pope</hi> Victor, <hi>in the</hi> 200, <hi>yeere excommunicated the Aſian Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops about the obſervation or keeping Eaſter day.</hi>-) So they ſay; but doe you ſpeake this to his credit, or to diſgrace his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Certainely it was a foule
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:240:56"/>fact that he did commit therein, and ſo it was cenſured by moſt learned and godly Biſhops of that age, and namely by S. <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus,</hi> who wrote vnto him pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely about the matter, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved him ſharpely for it, as he well deſerued. <hi>Jreneus in Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem per Epiſtolam graviter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectus eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Socrates Eccleſ. Hiſt. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 21. And that it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed other Chriſtian Biſhops beſides <hi>Jraeneus</hi> you ſhall finde in <hi>Euſeb. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Hiſt. Eccl. c.</hi> 23.24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The foure firſt gener all Councells not called by Popes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pope</hi> Silveſter <hi>in the</hi> (314) <hi>yeare called the firſt generall councell of Nice againſt the Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Hereſy.</hi>-) <hi>Baronius</hi> then is out in his reckoning of anno 325. <hi>Euſebius</hi> who liued in that time, and was well acquainted
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:240:56"/>with the buſineſſe, affirmeth that it was called by <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the Emperour, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>de vit. Conſtant. c.</hi> 6. and 7. And I thinke it were hard to name any auncient writer that denies it. The Councell it ſelfe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth ſo much in a Synodicall Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, Aegypt, Libia,</hi> and <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tapolis. Quoniam Dei gratiâ &amp; mandato Sanctiſſimi Jmpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris Conſtantini, qui nos ex va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis civitatibus, &amp; provinciis in vnum congregavit, magnum &amp; ſanctum Concilium Nicenum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actum eſt.—apud Socrat. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſ. c.</hi> 6. This caſe is ſo plaine that <hi>Pigh. Eccleſ. hier. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 1. calls generall Councells <hi>(Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Conſtantinum)</hi> though <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm.</hi> chid him for it, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. c.</hi> 13. <hi>To.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pope</hi> Damaſcus <hi>in the</hi> (367)
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:240:57"/>
                  <hi>yeare called the ſecond gener all Councell at Conſtantinople a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Macedonius <hi>the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique-</hi>) As true as <hi>Silveſter</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the firſt. <hi>Sozomen Hiſt. Ecleſ. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 7. ſaith directly that <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> the Emperour called it: &amp; the Councell it ſelfe in a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter writen to him,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> doth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that it was aſſembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>by vertue of a writ</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected from his (Imperiall) Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pope</hi> Caeleſtine (414) <hi>called the third generall Councell at E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus againſt</hi> Neſtorius <hi>the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retique,-</hi>) It ſeemes that Pope <hi>Caeleſtine</hi> himſelfe was not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at this Councell: But for the Councell it ſelfe it was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<q>
                     <hi>Authoritate &amp; nutu Theodoſii junioris, qui tum ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rient ale adminiſtravit imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium</hi> ſaith <hi>Evag. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</q>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:240:57"/>And <hi>Literae Jmperatoris erant ad Cyrillum &amp; ad alios omnes vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſanctarum Eccleſiarum Praeſides miſſae</hi>) <hi>Ibid.</hi> and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Councell in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beginning doe teſtify ſo much.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pope</hi> Leo (440) <hi>called the Fourth genera all Councell at Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon againſt the Heretique</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiches,-) Let the acts of the Councell ſpeake; which begin thus, <hi>In civitate Calcedonenſi Metropoli Provinciae Bythiniae facta est Synodus ex decreto pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſimorum Imperat. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni &amp; Marciani:</hi> and hee that reades the Epiſtles of <hi>Leo,</hi> ſhall finde in what humble and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſiue manner hee wrote di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times to the Emperour to call a Councell, not challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any authority therein to himſelfe, but intreating it as a
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:240:58"/>favour from his Lord the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. <hi>Vide Epiſtolam.</hi> 9. <hi>ad Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſ. &amp; Epiſt.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp; Epiſt.</hi> 23. <hi>ad Clerum &amp; Plebem Conſtantinop. &amp; Epiſt.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26. And thus you ſee how the foure Popes did call the firſt, foure generall Councels.</p>
               <p>For when your <hi>friend</hi> begins to ſpeake of the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> he begins to draw vpon the lees. And here <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who thinkes generall Councells profitable and convenient, but not abſolutely neceſſary for the Church <hi>l.</hi> 1 <hi>de concil. c.</hi> 10. when he comes to the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> he pleades for the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity thereof, <hi>vt pro aris &amp; focis, as Demetrius for Diana: Act.</hi> 19. Our trade is like to decay and be vndone, if that be toucht. <hi>Si tollamus autoritatem praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Eccleſiae &amp; Concilij (Triden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tini)</hi> then all will come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:240:58"/>
                  <hi>de effect ſaor. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 35. <hi>q. d.</hi> Though all other councells were expunged, yet that may ſtand by it ſelfe, and ſo long we ſhall ſtand. One thing more by the way I would haue you take notice of in <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> how when hee had firſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to proue that the firſt foure generall Councels were all called by Popes (juſt as your <hi>friend</hi> would haue it) yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after in the ſame chapter he ſets downe foure reaſons, why the Emperor did call call thoſe 4. Councels and not Popes alone <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Concil. to. cap.</hi> 13. <hi>to.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is confeſſed by divers lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Proteſtants, that the Romane Church was the true Mother Church, which Chriſt our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our planted: ſome for</hi> 300, <hi>yeeres, ſome for</hi> 400. <hi>yeares, ſome for</hi> 600. <hi>yeares, &amp;c.</hi>) Among other
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:240:59"/>particular.
<q>Churches planted by the Apoſtles, the Romane Church with the firſt was of ſpeciall note:</q> and the faith of the Romans in the beginning renowned through the whole world. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8. But what doth S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay more of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes in that place,<note place="margin">The Romiſh Church not the mother of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> then hee doth of the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where? Read 1. <hi>Theſ. v.</hi> 7.8. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 3.4. and you ſhall finde as great praiſe if not grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter given to them, then to the other. What would hee inferre hence? Did hee ever heare any Proteſtant confeſſe (becauſe he would ſo faine worke ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what out of their confeſſion) that the Romiſh Church, when it was at the beſt, was the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all Chriſtians? Or that the holy Catholique Church which we belieue in our Creed, was nothing elſe but the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:240:59"/>Church of Rome? Or, becauſe that Church was faithfull in the Apoſtles daies, doth it follow that it muſt needs continue ſo ſtill? <hi>Egeſippus</hi> an auncient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique writer ſaith, that ſo long as the Apoſtles liued, <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go pura &amp; incorrupta manſit Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, &amp;c. apud Euſeb. Eccl. Hiſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 29. And whereas hee talkes of 300 and 400. nay of 800. years, as if we did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Rome ſo long to haue bin the Church of Chriſt; tell him for his further learning, that we acknowledge her for a Church ſtill (though a moſt degenerate, and corrupted one:) Whoſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is full of Novelty, and her practiſe as full of pride, and cruelty; and yet a Church in reſpect of ſome truths that ſhee teacheth among many falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, as a man that is heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke and ready to dye, ceaſeth
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:240:60"/>not for all that to bee a man; ſo we likewiſe thinke of divers other Chriſtians in the world: though there be many errors in their doctrine, and much ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall in their liues, yet ſo long as they hold the foundation, the name of the Church is not to be denied them; and if your <hi>friend</hi> thinke otherwiſe tell him that his faith is never the better, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his charity is worſe then ours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The corruptions of Rome.</head>
               <p>But hee will deny perhaps that there are any ſuch corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as we ſpeake of, growne into the Church of Rome. What then meane ſo many grievous complaints made by men of ſpeciall note in that Church long before <hi>Luther</hi> was borne?<note place="margin">Bernard. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>antic. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on. ſerm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> What meant <hi>Bernard</hi> to ſay that there was <hi>putida tabes,</hi> a filthy
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:240:60"/>diſeaſe that had ſpred it ſelfe throughout all the parts of the Church? &amp; that <hi>Miniſtri Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti,</hi> in his time did <hi>ſervire Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſto?</hi> If nothing be amiſſe in the Church of Rome, what meant <hi>Paulus Tertius</hi> to ſet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine delegate Cardinals and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers a worke to giue their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice how reformation might be made? Or what meant thoſe Cardinalls to write ſuch a booke as they did (called <hi>Concilium delect. Card. &amp; aliorum Praelat.</hi>) which if you will read (as it is extant in <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>Concil. edit. per Crab. editionis Colon.</hi> 1551.) you ſhall find that their Church hath both <hi>rugas &amp; maculas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Concil. Trident. ſeſſ. <hi>22.</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eret. de O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſerb. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> vit. in cel bratione Miſſae.</note> as well in matter of doctrine as in manners. What meant the Councell of Trent to decree, that the Maſſe it ſelfe ought to be purged out of all ſuch abuſes, as <hi>vel avaritia, vel ſuperſtitio
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:240:61"/>induxit:</hi> if all were as it ſhould be, what needed ſuch a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of your Breviary and Miſſal, <hi>&amp; officium beatae virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis?</hi> But that they were <hi>refertae ſuperſtitionibus,</hi> and ſo confeſſed in <hi>Pij Quinti, conſtitut. ſuper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citat. offic. Beat. virginis:</hi> Read alſo his preface in <hi>Breviar, &amp; Miſſale reſtitut.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Indeficiency of faith not promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to one particular Church.</head>
               <p>Now let him anſwere him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, how it may bee true that Rome was once a ſound Church of Chriſt, and yet is not ſo now. Let him remember what <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>How is the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full City become a Harlot</hi>-) De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him to read that whole paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in the Prophet, and he ſhall finde how changing of the name, the words doe as well fit Rome in theſe daies, as ever
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:240:61"/>they did Ieruſalem then. And whereas he talkes of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God, it is but the ſame vanity that the Iewes were poſſeſſed with, when they ſtood ſo much vpon <hi>Templum Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, Jer.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 4. The promiſes that Chriſt made to his Church; <hi>that he would be with it to the end of the world: That hee would ſend the ſpirit of truth to abide with it for ever: that Hell gates ſhall not prevaile againſt it:</hi> They were made to the Catholique Church, and not to any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar one, ſuch as Rome is; and to that Catholique Church they haue beene and ever ſhall bee moſt truly performed. God will haue his Church vpon earth though Rome were as deepe buried vnder the earth, as now ſhe ſtands aboue it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And to end with a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration-)</hi> Hee doth well to end
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:240:62"/>with one, for I am ſure that from the beginning hitherto ſuch <hi>Arguments</hi> haue beene geaſon with your <hi>friend</hi> and if this bee one, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> never knew what demonſtrations meant: in that kinde of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the propoſitions ought to be evidently true: and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion to be drawne from the premiſes not by probable, but by neceſſary conſequence. And here is no ſuch matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Patriarchall and Epiſcopall ſeates of the Apostles not extinguiſhed.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That all the Patriarchall and Epiſcopall ſeates of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.-)</hi> This is not true; nay, in ſaying ſo he doth vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly overlaſh: For it is well knowne to the world, that there is at this day a Patriarch of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> to whoſe Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:240:62"/>are ſubiect all the Chriſtians of <hi>Aſia minor</hi> (excepting <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menia</hi> the leſſe, and <hi>Cilicia</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>Circaſſia, Mengrelia</hi> and <hi>Ruſſia;</hi> moreover that in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope it ſelfe the Chriſtians of <hi>Greece, Macedonia, Epirus, Thracia, Bulgaria, Raſcia, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via, Boſſina, Walachia, Molda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via, Podolia,</hi>- doe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Iuriſdiction of that Patriarch, and cannot endure the Biſhop of Rome; vnder this Patriarch there is the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan of <hi>Salonichi (Theſſolonica)</hi> and thirtie Churches of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in that one Citty: and no leſſe then ten <hi>Suffragan</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſubiect to his Iuriſdiction: beſides this the Metropolitan of <hi>Philippi,</hi> hath 150. Churches vnder him: <hi>Athens</hi> as many: Hee of <hi>Corinth</hi> hath a hundred; beſides all the Ilands of the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gean Sea, Conſtantinople</hi> it ſelfe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:240:63"/>the very ſeat of the Turkiſh Empire hath aboue twenty Churches of Chriſtians. Put all theſe together, and you ſhall ſee that Papiſts haue little cauſe to boaſt of their multitude, or to ſleight this Patriarch, as if there were but few Chriſtians ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject vnto him. There are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at this day Patriarchs, though poore ones of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> and great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Chriſtians that are ſubiect to each of them; though nothing ſo many in number as were wont to bee heretofore, (by reaſon of the Turkiſh ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and oppreſſion, vnder which they are brought:) yet neither ſo few that it can bee truely ſaid of the meaneſt of them, as your <hi>friend</hi> ventures to affirme of them all. <hi>(That they bee extinguiſhed and worne out many yeares ſince:)</hi> They be
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:240:63"/>poore, and ſuffer much affliction vnder the Turke, and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, and yet they may be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the worſe Chriſtians for all that. True piety and godlineſſe did never ſo much flouriſh in the Church, as when the Church it ſelfe was moſt perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and afflicted by Tyrants. <hi>Schola Crucis, eſt Schola Lucis, &amp; ſemen Eccleſiae, eſt ſanguis Martyrum;</hi> and therefore they that make temporall proſperity a note to know the Catholique Church by, (as generally our Ieſuites doe) ſpeake more like Epicures, then Divines and Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Beſides your <hi>friend</hi> ſhewes himſelfe very ignorant in the ſtate of his owne Romiſh Church, if he doe not know that the Pope at this day doth vſually create certaine titular Praelates; Whereof one is called Patriarch
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:240:64"/>of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> the other of <hi>Antioch,</hi> another of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> It is true that theſe all are but meere puppets and Idols, and poſſeſſe not a foote of revenew or the leaſt part of Iuriſdiction in thoſe places whereof they beare names; yet your <hi>friend</hi> ſhould not haue denied that there were any ſuch Patriarchs, ſeeing they are Creatures of the Popes owne making, whoſe greateſt vſe is to gull the world vnder thoſe names, as if thoſe foure Patriarchs did performe him obedience: when indeed they bee but foure vizzards in compariſon of the Patriarchs themſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Only the Church of Rome, the ſeat of Saint</hi> Peter <hi>ſtands at this day-)</hi> Let him not ſtand too much vpon the ſtanding of his Church:<note place="margin">Rome no ſound Church of Chriſt.</note> For ſure the leggs
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:240:64"/>thereof are not ſo ſound as they ſhould bee; a church may be worne out as well by diſeaſes bred inwardly in her body, as by the violence of externall perſecution: If Rome bee free from this latter, yet a great part of the world thinkes her ill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in her inward, and vitall parts. She thinkes not ſo her ſelfe: no more doth many a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man, but will ſay he is well, when he is ready to giue vp the Ghoſt. <hi>Sacerdotium quod intus cecidit, foris diu ſtare non poteſt, Greg. Mor.</hi> You ſee the falſhood of thoſe propoſitions vpon which his demonſtration is built, ſee now how looſely his concluſion hangs vpon thoſe propoſitions, though I ſhould grant them to be true. If there be any ſenſe at all in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of the parts together, this it is. All the other Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chall
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:240:65"/>Churches are fallen: One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rome is not fallen: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhall never fall. Let him take his anſwere from S. <hi>Paul Rom.</hi> 11.17. <hi>If ſome of the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches be broken off, and thou being a wild Oliue tree, &amp;c.</hi> Now let him remember to what Church Saint <hi>Paul</hi> there writes, and what they were to whom hee gaue ſuch earneſt premonition to take heed leaſt for their infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity God ſhould caſt them off, as hee had done the Iewes in their ſight. This had beene a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry needleſſe admonition eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially from the Apoſtle to the Romanes, if he knew certainly that God had promiſed them ſuch indeficiency of faith, that whatſoever became of other Churches, theirs ſhould never turne Infidell. <hi>Be not high min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded but feare,</hi> ſaith hee vnto them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. and againe, <hi>If
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:240:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>God ſpared not the naturall bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches (the Jewes) take heed leaſt hee alſo ſpare not thee, v.</hi> 21. and againe. <hi>Behold the goodneſſe of God towards thee (if you conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in his goodneſſe) otherwiſe thou ſhalt be cut off, v.</hi> 22. And yet your <hi>friend</hi> would make you thinke that the Romanes haue no cauſe to feare, and that they cannot be cut off, and all by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of an imaginary promiſe which hee ſuppoſeth Chriſt made to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: by which reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> (iffs) were but <hi>Panici timoris:</hi> Hee feared where no feare was: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might well haue ſpared all the breath he ſpent that way.</p>
               <p>To conclude let mee now at the <hi>Parting,</hi> giue him a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration out of theſe words of the Apoſtle. That Church which may poſſibly bee cut
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:240:66"/>off from Chriſt and fall into infidelity, is not the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church. But it is poſſible the Romiſh Church may be cut off from Chriſt, and fall into infidelity. <hi>Teſte Apoſtolo vt ſupra.</hi> Therefore the Romiſh Church is not the true Catholique Church.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:240:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
